Guide to the North Carolina Association of Jewish Women Records, 1937-2000 RL.10188
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
North Carolina Association of Jewish Women records
1937-2000
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
North Carolina Association of Jewish Women
RL.10188
4 Linear Feet
The North Carolina Association of Jewish Women (NCAJW) was founded by Sarah Weil in 1921 with the intent “to deepen the religious life, to stimulate interest and Jewish affairs, and to increase Jewish community activity.” The organization’s projects included administration of a scholarship fund, sponsorship of the NCA of Jewish Youth (founded in 1946), and help towards purchasing books of Jewish interest for the libraries of North Carolina. The materials in this collection primarily document the daily business activities of the NCAJW and include programs and reports from annual conventions and meetings, membership, correspondence to and from Yetta Leder (President and Membership Chair of the NCAJW), financial records such as balance sheets, budgets, and annual contributions, year books, and reports, correspondence, and photographs related to the organization’s various projects.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48-hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Historical note
The North Carolina Association of Jewish Women (NCAJW) was founded by Sarah Weil in 1921 with the intent “to deepen the religious life, to stimulate interest and Jewish affairs, and to increase Jewish community activity.” It was the only organization of its kind with the purpose of uniting of Jewish women of Reform, Orthodox, and Conservative leanings into a state-wide group. The organization’s projects included administration of a scholarship fund, sponsorship of the NCA of Jewish Youth (founded in 1946), and help towards purchasing books of Jewish interest for the libraries of North Carolina.
The NCAJW and the North Carolina Association of Jewish Men (NCAJM) jointly sponsored the traveling rabbi program (aka Circuit Riding Rabbis) to serve the small Jewish communities of the Carolinas, the North Carolina Home for the Jewish Aged (which was dedicated in 1967; the name was changed to Blumenthal Jewish Home in honor of Mr. I.D. Blumenthal). In 1988 the NCAJW and NCAJM formally merged and the Carolinas Association of Jewish Women and Men was established.
Arrangement
The materials in this collection are arranged chronologically.
Collection Overview
The materials in this collection primarily document the daily business activities of the NCAJW and include programs and reports from annual conventions and meetings, membership, correspondence to and from Yetta Leder (President and Membership Chair of the NCAJW), financial records such as balance sheets, budgets, and annual contributions, year books, and reports, correspondence, and photographs related to the organization’s various projects.
The collection also includes a small amount of materials related to the NCAJM and the NCA of Jewish Youth.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The North Carolina Association of Jewish Women records were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as part of the Jewish Heritage Foundation of North Carolina Collection in June, 2014.
Jews -- North Carolina; Women -- Societies and clubs; Jewish women -- United States.; North Carolina Association of Jewish Women
- North Carolina Association of Jewish Women records, 1937-2000
  - Annual Year Books, 1937-1938, 1940-1943, 1946-1949, 1953, 1956-1957, 1961-1962 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Annual conventions and conferences, 1941, 1958-1973 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - [Circuit Riding Rabbi Project], 1952-1954, 1971 and undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Memberships, Assn. of Jewish Women, 1953-1956, 1964-1965 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Life Magazine, "Traveling Synagogue, North Carolina Rabbi Holds Service in Bus", 1955 September (Box 2)
  - NCA Jewish Youth, 1957-1958 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - North Carolina Association of Jewish Men Miscellaneous, 1957-1977, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Jewish Youth Assoc. Camp Registration, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - NCAJW Membership, 1960-1963; 1 of 2 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - NCAJW Membership, 1960-1963; 2 of 2 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - History of the North Carolina Association of Jewish Women, 1961, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Membership, 1963-1998 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - NCAJ Rabbis, 1964, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - NCAJW Meeting Minutes, 1964-1966, 1972-1974, 1986-1987 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence to Yetta Leder, 1964-1967, 1971-1973, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence from Yetta Leder, 1964-1968; 1 of 3 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence from Yetta Leder, 1964-1968; 2 of 3 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence from Yetta Leder, 1964-1968; 3 of 3 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - NC Home for the Jewish Aged, 1964-1978; 1 of 2 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - NC Home for the Jewish Aged, 1964-1978; 2 of 2 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - North Carolina Council of Women's Organization Minutes, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - NCAJW Membership, 1965-1966 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Financial Records, 1966, 1995-1998 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence from Yetta Leder, 1966-1969, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - NCAJW NC Jewish Population Census, 1968; 1 of 2 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - NCAJW NC Jewish Population Census, 1968; 2 of 2 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Clippings, 1971, 1983 and undated (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Carolina Assoc. of Jewish Women & Men Membership, 1995-1996 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - North Carolina Assoc. of Jewish Women Membership, 1996-1999; 1 of 3 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - North Carolina Assoc. of Jewish Women Membership, 1996-1999; 2 of 3 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - North Carolina Assoc. of Jewish Women Membership, 1996-1999; 3 of 3 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, 2000 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - N.C. Association of Jewish Men Religious School Curriculum Junior High, undated (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Stationery, undated (Box 3, Folder 15)